Guide to the Horace Day Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Horace Day papers
1728-1915
1833-1874
GEN MSS 950
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2
(5 boxes)
The papers contain letters, writings, and records of the Day family. Series I holds letters sent to Horace Day from his parents Gad and Roxanna Day, his brother George Edward Day (Yale 1833), his cousin Lucinda Day, and his friends, Yale classmates, and colleagues including Edward E. Atwater, Erasmus Darwin Hudson, Charles Backus McLean, and Noah Porter. Also present are letters of recommendation written on Day's behalf by Jeremiah Day, Eleazar T. Fitch, Anthony D. Stanley, and Nathaniel W. Taylor. Personal Papers includes material investigating Gad Day's military service and a proposal from E. S. Goodrich to publish the Pioneer newspaper at St. Paul, Minnesota. Also present is a manuscript broadside announcing a music concert at sea and a printed broadside advertising Thomas Kimpton's Parcel Express shipping service from London to "all parts of the kingdom" as well as the colonies and and North America; they may be related to Day's trips to Europe in the late 1850s. Series II holds autograph manuscripts and typescripts of writings by Day and his daughter Sarah Day Woodward, including addresses delivered before the New Haven Colony Historical Society. Also in the series are a group of manuscript sermons by an unidentified author, dated 1728-1833, and newspaper clippings related to the history of New Haven, Connecticut, dated 1857-1915. Series III holds five financial ledgers for the Day & Fitch company dating 1845-1855, and one personal account book recording Day's expenses, 1868-1874. Series IV holds two volumes of Day's notes made during meetings of the New Haven Board of Education, 1882-1890.
Day, Horace, 1816-1902
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sarah Day Woodward, 1936.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Gad Day Family Papers (MS 1225). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Horace Day (1816-1902)
Horace Day was born in Pittsfield, Massachusetts, on November 5, 1816, the son of Gad and Roxanna Rice Day; the family moved to New Haven, Connecticut, in 1822. Day studied at the Hopkins Grammar School and graduated from Yale College in 1836. After briefly teaching school he studied for three years in Yale Seminary, but was never ordained. Day was for several years a publisher and bookseller in New Haven as a partner with L. W. Fitch in the firm of Day & Fitch, afterward becoming editor of the New Haven Journal and Courier, and assistant editor of the Cincinnati Daily Gazette. He returned to New Haven in 1856, and in 1860 was appointed superintendent of the public schools of New Haven, an office he held for five years. In 1868 he became secretary of the New Haven Board of Education and served the city in that capacity to the end of his life. Day was one of the founders of the New Haven Colony Historical Society and was the institution's first secretary. Day's antiquarian interests led to his being often consulted regarding early landmarks and local history, and he assisted in the compilation of several genealogies. In 1887 Day became secretary of the Yale Class of 1836. He died in New Haven on July 22, 1902.
Sarah Cazneau Day Woodward (1855-1946)
Sarah Cazneau Day (1855-1946) was the daughter of Horace and Sarah Rice Day; she married Richard W. Woodward (1846-1931, Yale 1867) in 1881. An antiquarian like her father, Sarah Day Woodward was an active member of the Daughters of the American Revolution, and the author of Early New Haven (New Haven, Conn.: Price, Lee & Adkins Co., 1912).
Scope and Contents
The papers contain letters, writings, and records of the Day family. Series I holds letters sent to Horace Day from his parents Gad and Roxanna Day, his brother George Edward Day (Yale 1833), his cousin Lucinda Day, and his friends, Yale classmates, and colleagues including Edward E. Atwater, Erasmus Darwin Hudson, Charles Backus McLean, and Noah Porter. Also present are letters of recommendation written on Day's behalf by Jeremiah Day, Eleazar T. Fitch, Anthony D. Stanley, and Nathaniel W. Taylor. Personal Papers includes material investigating Gad Day's military service and a proposal from E. S. Goodrich to publish the Pioneer newspaper at St. Paul, Minnesota. Also present is a manuscript broadside announcing a music concert at sea and a printed broadside advertising Thomas Kimpton's Parcel Express shipping service from London to "all parts of the kingdom" as well as the colonies and North America; they may be related to Day's trips to Europe in the late 1850s. Series II holds autograph manuscripts and typescripts of writings by Day and his daughter Sarah Day Woodward, including addresses delivered before the New Haven Colony Historical Society. Also in the series are a group of manuscript sermons by an unidentified preacher, dated 1728-1833, and newspaper clippings related to the history of New Haven, Connecticut, dated 1857-1915. Series III holds five financial ledgers for the Day & Fitch company dating 1845-1855, and one personal account book recording Day's expenses, 1868-1874. Series IV holds two volumes of Day's notes made during meetings of the New Haven Board of Education, 1882-1890.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1814-1867. II. Writings, 1728-1915. III. Financial Records, 1845-1874. IV. New Haven Board of Education Minutes, 1882-1890.
Booksellers and bookselling -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Education -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Publishers and publishing -- Connecticut -- New Haven; New Haven (Conn.) -- History; Broadsides -- London (England) -- 19th century; Ledgers (account books) -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 19th century; Minute books -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 19th century; Sermons -- Connecticut -- 18th century; Speeches (documents) -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 19th century; Atwater, Edward E. (Edward Elias), 1816-1887; Baldwin, William Barlow, 1817-1853; Day family; Day, Gad, 1784-1873; Day, George Edward, 1815-1905; Day, Horace, 1816-1902; Day, Jeremiah, 1773-1867; Fitch, Eleazar T. (Eleazar Thompson), 1791-1871; Fitch, L. W. (Lucius Wooster), 1820-1908; Hudson, Erasmus Darwin, 1806-1880; McLean, Charles Backus, 1815-1873; Porter, Noah, 1811-1892; Stanley, Anthony D. (Anthony Dumond), 1810-1853; Taylor, Nathaniel W. (Nathaniel William), 1786-1858; Woodward, Sarah Day, 1855-1946; Day & Fitch; New Haven Colony Historical Society; New Haven (Conn.). Board of Education; Thomas Kimpton & Co
- Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1814-1867; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Correspondence, and Personal Papers.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I holds letters sent to Horace Day from his parents Gad and Roxanna Day, his brother George Edward Day (Yale 1833), his cousin Lucinda Day, and his friends, Yale classmates, and colleagues including Edward E. Atwater, Erasmus Darwin Hudson, Charles Backus McLean, and Noah Porter. Also present are letters of recommendation written on Day's behalf by Jeremiah Day, Eleazar T. Fitch, Anthony D. Stanley, and Nathaniel W. Taylor. Personal Papers includes material investigating Gad Day's military service and a proposal from E. S. Goodrich to publish the Pioneer newspaper at St. Paul, Minnesota. Also present is a manuscript broadside announcing a music concert at sea and a printed broadside advertising Thomas Kimpton's Parcel Express shipping service from London to "all parts of the kingdom" as well as the colonies and North America; they may be related to Day's trips to Europe in the late 1850s.
  - Correspondence
    - General correspondence, A-Z, 1834-1867 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Atwater, Edward E., 1841 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Baldwin, William Barlow, 1836-1838 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Beach, 1836-1843 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cowles, 1838-1843 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Day, George Edward, 1833-1842 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Day, Roxanna, 1836-1843 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      General note
      Includes letters written or co-written by Gad Day and Lucinda Day
    - Hudson, Erasmus D., 1837-1838 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - McLean, Charles B., 1836-1844 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Moore, James, 1836-1837 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Porter, 1837-1843 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Porter, Noah, 1839-1844 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Smith, 1842-1843 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letters of recommendation, 1836-1841 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Personal Papers
    - Papers concerning Gad Day's military service, 1814-1852 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Proposal to publish a newspaper in St. Paul, Minnesota, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Broadsides, 1857, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Writings, 1728-1915; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series II is organized into three subseries: Horace Day Writings, Sarah Day Woodward Writings, and Other Writings.
  The series holds autograph manuscripts and typescripts of writings by Day and his daughter Sarah Day Woodward, including addresses delivered before the New Haven Colony Historical Society. Also in the series are a group of manuscript sermons by an unidentified preacher, dated 1728-1833, and newspaper clippings related to the history of New Haven, Connecticut, dated 1857-1915.
  - Horace Day Writings
    - Linonian Society oration, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Genealogy notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - On English Congregationalists, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - On New Haven history, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - Sarah Day Woodward Writings
    - Genealogy notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - On New Haven history, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous, 1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Other Writings
    - Sermons, author unidentified, 1728-1833 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Classroom notes, author unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Newspaper clippings about New Haven and Springfield, Massachusetts, 1857-1915 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Financial Records, 1845-1874; Series III; 1.08; (3 boxes)
  Series III holds one personal account book recording Day's expenses and five financial ledgers for the Day & Fitch company of New Haven.
  - Horace Day personal accounts, 1868-1874 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 32)
  - Day & Fitch account book, 1845-1847 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 33)
  - Day & Fitch account book, 1846 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 34)
  - Day & Fitch account book, 1845-1855 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Day & Fitch account book, 1846 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Day & Fitch account book, 1847-1848 (Box 5, Folder 37)
- New Haven Board of Education Minutes, 1882-1890; Series IV; 2
  Series IV holds two volumes of Day's rough minutes made during meetings of the New Haven Board of Education.
  - Minutes, 1882-1886 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Minutes, 1886-1890 (Box 5, Folder 39)